export const jambLiterature = [
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on  J.C. De Graft's Sons and  Daughters",
    question:
      "‘I simply don't understand what's the matter with everybody today. Everybody let me down, and the speaker above is referring to __.",
    options: [
      "Fosuwa and Maidservant",
      "Hannah and George",
      "Aaron and Maanan",
      "Lawyer B and Mrs. B",
    ],
    answer: "Hannah and George",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on  J.C. De Graft's Sons and  Daughters",
    question: "Maanan expresses dislike for Lawyer B because of __.",
    options: [
      "his condemnation of her choice of career",
      "his recent advances towards her",
      "the betrayal of her father's trust",
      "the betrayal of his wife's trust",
    ],
    answer: "his condemnation of her choice of career",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on  J.C. De Graft's Sons and  Daughters",
    question: "The traditional order in the play is represented by __.",
    options: ["Mrs. B", "Hannah", "Maanan", "Aunt"],
    answer: "Aunt",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on  J.C. De Graft's Sons and  Daughters",
    question: "Where does the play take place?",
    options: [
      "On the street",
      "In George's place",
      "In Aunt's house",
      "In Ofosu's place",
    ],
    answer: "In Aunt's house",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet",
    question:
      "'O deadly sin! O rude unthankfulness! Thy fault our law calls death, but the kind Prince, Taking thy part, hath rushed aside the law And turned that black word...' Deadly sin refers to the __.",
    options: [
      "suicide of Juliet",
      "suicide of Romeo",
      "murder of Paris",
      "murder of Tybalt",
    ],
    answer: "murder of Tybalt",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet",
    question: "The play is mostly written in __.",
    options: ["blank verse", "free verse", "metres", "foot"],
    answer: "blank verse",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet",
    question:
      "'O serpent heart, hid with a flowering face!' The statement above refers to __.",
    options: ["Juliet", "Romeo", "Tybalt", "Benvolio"],
    answer: "Romeo",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet",
    question: "The spatial setting of the play is __.",
    options: ["Athens", "Verona", "Padua", "Venice"],
    answer: "Verona",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet",
    question: "Romeo is banished to Mantua because he __.",
    options: [
      "kills Tybalt in a street duel",
      "marries Juliet without parental consent",
      "attends Capulet's party uninvited",
      "attempts to kill Paris, his rival",
    ],
    answer: "kills Tybalt in a street duel",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joys of Motherhood.",
    question: "In the novel, the society puts high value on __.",
    options: [
      "egalitarianism",
      "male ascendancy",
      "procreation",
      "gender equity",
    ],
    answer: "procreation",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joys of Motherhood.",
    question:
      "The medicine man links the lump discovered on the head of Nnu Ego at birth, to the __.",
    options: [
      "possession of physical admirable qualities that makes her an epitome of perfection.",
      "sickness and joblessness",
      "disagreement and humiliation",
      "wound inflicted on the slave woman buried with Agbadi’s wife",
    ],
    answer: "wound inflicted on the slave woman buried with Agbadi’s wife",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joys of Motherhood.",
    question: "The constant companions of Nnaife's family are __.",
    options: [
      "togetherness and happiness",
      "poverty and hunger",
      "sickness and joblessness",
      "disagreement and humiliation",
    ],
    answer: "poverty and hunger",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Ferdinand Oyano's The Old Man and the Medal.",
    question:
      "The disagreement between Mvondo and Nti centres on the latter’s claim to have __.",
    options: [
      "assisted Meka in getting the medal",
      "eaten the entire entrails of a sheep",
      "eaten more than his share of the food",
      "been in a white man’s office",
    ],
    answer: "been in a white man’s office",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Ferdinand Oyano's The Old Man and the Medal.",
    question: "Meka can be best described as __.",
    options: [
      "an egocentric old man",
      "a simple-hearted old man",
      "an impulsive old man",
      "an old religious bigot",
    ],
    answer: "a simple-hearted old man",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Ferdinand Oyano's The Old Man and the Medal.",
    question: "In the novel, the colonialists treat the Africans with __.",
    options: ["Kids’ gloves", "disdain", "indifference", "honour"],
    answer: "disdain",
  },

  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The Ministry of Peace is concerned with making __.",
    options: ["instruments", "weapons", "wars", "reconciliation"],
    answer: "wars",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The subject matter of the novel is __.",
    options: [
      "totalitarian dictatorship",
      "exploitation and cruelty",
      "retributive justice",
      "class segregation",
    ],
    answer: "totalitarian dictatorship",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "How did Winston start his rebellion against the state __.",
    options: [
      "By engaging in anti-party activities",
      "By keeping a private diary",
      "When he started a secret affair",
      "When he spied on the party",
    ],
    answer: "By keeping a private diary",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The party seeks power for __.",
    options: ["the nation", "its own sake", "its members", "people's sake"],
    answer: "its own sake",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "As the dancers move through paths strewn with glass chips, the images in Adeoti's Naked Soles change from __.",
    options: [
      "joy to excitement",
      "inaction to action",
      "pain to grief",
      "sorrow to joy",
    ],
    answer: "pain to grief",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "In Rubadiri's An African Thunderstorm, the poem says that during a thunderstorm in the village __.",
    options: [
      "women cook their food",
      "children play in the rain",
      "children are delighted while women move in and out",
      "both women and children are delighted",
    ],
    answer: "children are delighted while women move in and out",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "In the lines, 'Yet in their finger upon Our navel The midwives of the spirit say They feel a foetal throb,' from Acquah's In the Navel of the Soul, the dominant literary device used is __.",
    options: ["epigram", "allegory", "enjambment", "rhythm"],
    answer: "enjambment",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "In Kunene's A Heritage of Liberation, the poet persona requests that the weapons of warfare be handed to their __.",
    options: ["friends", "relations", "grandchildren", "families"],
    answer: "grandchildren",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question: "The predominant device in Launko's End of the War is __.",
    options: ["onomatopoeia", "antithesis", "oxymoron", "paradox"],
    answer: "paradox",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "The theme of the poem Give Me The Minstrel's Seat centres on __.",
    options: ["divorce", "fortune", "marriage", "companionship"],
    answer: "companionship",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "The poet persona in Marvell's To His Coy Mistress is willing to praise the lady's eyes for __.",
    options: [
      "thirty thousand years",
      "six decades",
      "two centuries",
      "a century",
    ],
    answer: "thirty thousand years",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question: "In Lawrence's Bat, the poet persona mistakes the bats for __.",
    options: ["owls", "swallows", "pipistrello", "sparrows"],
    answer: "swallows",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question:
      "In Eliot's Journey of the Magi, the magi are aided on their journey by __.",
    options: ["donkeys", "horses", "camels", "chariots"],
    answer: "camels",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from African; Soyinka, (ed.) Poems of Black Africa; Senanu K.E. and Vincent T. (eds.): A selection of African Poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eds.) Exam Focus: literature in English; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides and Nwoga, D. I. (ed): West African Verse.",
    question: "According to Cope’s Sonnet VII, poetry is basically __.",
    options: ["boring", "therapeutic", "philosophical", "inspiring"],
    answer: "therapeutic",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "A play which mainly aims at provoking excessive laughter is called",
    options: ["tragi-comedy", "comedy", "a farce", "satire"],
    answer: "a farce",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Both comedy and tragedy have",
    options: ["happy ending", "climax", "tragic hero", "stanza"],
    answer: "climax",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "A formal dignified speech or writing praising a person or a thing for past or present deeds is",
    options: ["premiere", "eulogy", "anthology", "lampoon"],
    answer: "eulogy",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The narrative style in which the hero tells his own story directly is the",
    options: ["objective", "subjective", "first-person", "third-person"],
    answer: "first-person",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The physical, historical or cultural background of a literary work is referred to as",
    options: ["episode", "plot", "time", "setting"],
    answer: "setting",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "A plot structure that defies chronology can be described as",
    options: ["open-ended", "circular", "episodic", "organic"],
    answer: "circular",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Pun as a literary device deals with",
    options: [
      "placing two opposite phrases",
      "placing words side by side",
      "playing on words",
      "arrangement of words",
    ],
    answer: "playing on words",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "In a narrative poem, the poet attempts to",
    options: [
      "summarize a story",
      "describe a place",
      "preach a sermon",
      "tell a story",
    ],
    answer: "tell a story",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The account of experiences of an individual during the course of a journey is known as",
    options: ["a travelogue", "an autobiography", "a catalogue", "a memoir"],
    answer: "a travelogue",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Satirical writing employs",
    options: ["epigram", "synecdoche", "irony", "onomatopoeia"],
    answer: "irony",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the questions.",
    question: "The person being addressed above is a",
    options: ["soldier", "student", "domestic servant", "lawyer"],
    answer: "soldier",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the questions.",
    question: "From the tone of the speech above, the speaker is obviously",
    options: ["enraged", "lackadaisical", "elated", "happy"],
    answer: "enraged",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The mood conveyed in the excerpt above is one of",
    options: ["sadness", "frustration", "sympathy", "dilemma"],
    answer: "sadness",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The rhyme scheme in the excerpt above is",
    options: ["bbaa", "aabb", "abab", "abba"],
    answer: "aabb",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The subject matter of the extract above is",
    options: ["storm", "sea waves", "house movement", "earthquake"],
    answer: "earthquake",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "From the poem above, shadow means",
    options: [
      "famine",
      "bleak future",
      "period of sufferings",
      "abstract ideas",
    ],
    answer: "period of sufferings",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The speaker in the excerpt above is",
    options: ["hopeless", "uncertain", "afraid", "confident"],
    answer: "confident",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet.",
    question: "The play reaches the point of denouncement",
    options: [
      "at the family feast",
      "when Romeo kills Paris at the tomb",
      "at the reconciliation of the feuding families",
      "when Romeo is informed of Juliet’s death",
    ],
    answer: "at the reconciliation of the feuding families",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet.",
    question: "The news of Juliet's death is broken to Romeo in Mantua by",
    options: ["Balthasar", "Friar Lawrence", "Boy", "Friar John"],
    answer: "Balthasar",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet.",
    question: "In the play, Mercutio can be described as",
    options: ["fraudulent", "quarrelsome", "gentle", "kind-hearted"],
    answer: "quarrelsome",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet.",
    question: "The plot of the play is",
    options: ["simple", "complicated", "convoluted", "chronological"],
    answer: "complicated",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Ferdinand Oyono's The Old Man and the Medal.",
    question:
      "The heavy downpour on the night of Meka's investiture symbolizes",
    options: ["revelation", "mockery", "conviction", "blessing"],
    answer: "mockery",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Ferdinand Oyono's The Old Man and the Medal.",
    question:
      "Vandermayer's attitude and action towards Meka illustrates the church's",
    options: ["despondency", "suspicion", "infuriation", "hypocrisy"],
    answer: "hypocrisy",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question: "For attempted murder, Nnaife was jailed for",
    options: ["four months", "three months", "five months", "two months"],
    answer: "two months",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question:
      "In the novel, Nwokocha Agbadi is famous for his oratorical powers and",
    options: ["height", "treachery", "illiteracy", "wealth"],
    answer: "wealth",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta's The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question:
      "In the novel, the handing over of a baby boy in a dream to Nnu Ego by her personal god signifies",
    options: ["reincarnation", "future blessing", "idol worship", "doom"],
    answer: "future blessing",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four.",
    question: "The novel draws a picture of",
    options: [
      "a useless past",
      "a totalitarian future",
      "an unstable moment",
      "a peaceful atmosphere",
    ],
    answer: "a totalitarian future",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four.",
    question:
      "The power and oppression of an irresistible evil debased Winston's dreams of",
    options: [
      "freedom and democracy",
      "internal security",
      "wealth and capitalism",
      "sovereignty",
    ],
    answer: "freedom and democracy",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four.",
    question: "Room 101 symbolizes a place of",
    options: ["rest", "fun", "humiliation", "tour"],
    answer: "humiliation",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four.",
    question: "The novel can be described as",
    options: ["optimistic", "antagonistic", "persuasive", "pessimistic"],
    answer: "pessimistic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "In *Naked Soles*, Adeoti writes that the carnival of naked soles dances through",
    options: [
      "scorching sun",
      "a dirty room",
      "blooming thorns",
      "a cloudy atmosphere",
    ],
    answer: "scorching sun",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "In Rubadiri's *An African Thunderstorm*, the thunderstorm begins with",
    options: [
      "rain from the west",
      "clouds from the east",
      "rain from the east",
      "clouds from the west",
    ],
    answer: "clouds from the west",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question: "The theme of Acquah's *In the Navel of the Soul* is",
    options: [
      "the conflict of traditions",
      "ensuring that traditions were strictly observed",
      "the futility of man and his tradition",
      "the strength in diversity of culture and traditional views",
    ],
    answer: "the futility of man and his tradition",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "In Kuene’s *A Heritage of Liberation*, the persona is concerned with the",
    options: [
      "people's struggle for survival",
      "criticism of modern tradition",
      "intolerance of the new generation",
      "celebration of African tradition",
    ],
    answer: "people's struggle for survival",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question: "Lanko’s *End of the War* portrays the",
    options: [
      "silence of",
      "usefulness of praise singers",
      "irony of life",
      "arrangement of war",
    ],
    answer: "irony of life",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "'Woman cannot exist except by man, What is there in that to vex some of them so?' The statement above from the poem *Give Me The Minstrel's Seat* exemplifies",
    options: [
      "litotes",
      "rhetorical question",
      "transferred epithet",
      "synecdoche",
    ],
    answer: "rhetorical question",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "Marvell, in *To His Coy Mistress* uses the imagery of Coy death to",
    options: [
      "appreciate God's power",
      "underscore life's transience",
      "condemn the lady",
      "scare the lady",
    ],
    answer: "underscore life's transience",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question: "To sustain the interest of readers, Lawrence in *Bat* uses",
    options: ["elision", "hyperbole", "suspense", "oxymoron"],
    answer: "suspense",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "'With a running stream and a water-mill beating the darkness. And three trees on the low sky.' In the excerpt above from Eliot's *Journey of the Magi*, the dominant literary device is",
    options: ["oxymoron", "personification", "hyperbole", "alliteration"],
    answer: "personification",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) *New Poetry from Africa*; Soyinka (ed.): *Poems of Black Africa*; Senanu K. E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): *A Selection of African Poetry*; Unukoro, M. et al (eds.): *Exam Focus: Literature in English*; Eruvbetine, A.E. et al (eds.): *Longman Examination Guides*; and Nwoga, D.I (ed): *West African Verse*.",
    question: "The tone of Cope's *Sonnet VII* is generally",
    options: ["persuasive", "humorous", "optimistic", "mournful"],
    answer: "mournful",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The large space above the proscenium in a theatre from which the scenes are controlled is called",
    options: ["aside", "setting", "anachronism", "flies"],
    answer: "flies",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The repetition of single words or phrases at the beginning of lines is",
    options: ["assonance", "parallelism", "onomatopoeia", "alliteration"],
    answer: "parallelism",
  },
  {
    question: "A ballad is meant to be",
    options: ["acted", "sung", "discussed", "read"],
    answer: "sung",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "In drama, dramaturge is he who",
    options: [
      "writes or edits plays",
      "feature in a play",
      "directs a play",
      "acts a film",
    ],
    answer: "writes or edits plays",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Travelogue is a work of art written",
    options: [
      "by a famous playwright",
      "before the death of the author",
      "by an unpopular novelist",
      "on a journey",
    ],
    answer: "on a journey",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Plays are basically meant to",
    options: [
      "change the world",
      "keep people out of trouble",
      "be ready for pleasure",
      "be presented on stage",
    ],
    answer: "be presented on stage",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "A character who re-enacts familiar experiences that readers easily identify with is",
    options: [
      "round character",
      "flat character",
      "stock character",
      "static character",
    ],
    answer: "stock character",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "The plot of a story generally refers to the",
    options: [
      "intrigue made by a character against the hero",
      "way the writer ends the story",
      "way in which the events of the story are organised",
      "way in which the writer begins the story",
    ],
    answer: "way in which the events of the story are organised",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based  on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The metric pattern in a line of poetry with five stressed and five unstressed syllables is",
    options: [
      "trochaic decametre",
      "dactylic metre",
      "iambic pentameter",
      "anapaestic metre",
    ],
    answer: "iambic pentameter",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on J.C. De Graft's *Sons and Daughters*.",
    question: "Who is the paternal aunt to Aaron and Maanan?",
    options: ["Mrs Bonu", "Hannah", "Fosuwa", "Adwao"],
    answer: "Fosuwa",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on J.C. De Graft's *Sons and Daughters*.",
    question: "From the play, George is a",
    options: ["laboratory assistant", "pharmacist", "nurse", "medical doctor"],
    answer: "pharmacist",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on J.C. De Graft's *Sons and Daughters*.",
    question:
      '"If you touch me, I shall smash your face with this bottle." The statement is made by',
    options: [
      "Maanan to lawyer B",
      "Maanan to Mrs Bonu",
      "James to Awere",
      "Awere to Aaron",
    ],
    answer: "Maanan to lawyer B",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on J.C. De Graft's *Sons and Daughters*.",
    question: "The issue at stake is that",
    options: [
      "Maanan is trying to compromise",
      "Lawyer B is trying to kiss Maanan",
      "James sees Awere as a bad influence",
      "Mrs Bonu is taunting Maanan for loving her husband",
    ],
    answer: "Lawyer B is trying to kiss Maanan",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s *Romeo and Juliet*.",
    question:
      '"The all-seeing sun, Ne\'er saw match since first the world begun." The lines above were spoken by',
    options: [
      "Count Paris in praise of Juliet",
      "Romeo in praise of Juliet",
      "Romeo in praise of Roseline",
      "Lady Capulet in praise of Roseline",
    ],
    answer: "Romeo in praise of Juliet",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s *Romeo and Juliet*.",
    question: "The major role of Mercutio in the play is to",
    options: [
      "serve as a contrast to Romeo",
      "aid and abet Romeo's passion",
      "annoy Tybalt",
      "accompany Romeo to Friar Lawrence",
    ],
    answer: "serve as a contrast to Romeo",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on William Shakespeare’s *Romeo and Juliet*.",
    question:
      "The play shares the feature of classical tragedy through the use of",
    options: ["violence on stage", "chorus", "comic relief", "flashback"],
    answer: "chorus",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s *The Joy of Motherhood*.",
    question:
      "As a symbol of material success and fulfilment, Ibuzza community places a lot of importance on",
    options: ["childbirth", "wealth", "male child", "female child"],
    answer: "male child",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s *The Joy of Motherhood*.",
    question: "Ona on her dying bed appeals to Agbadi to",
    options: [
      "give her a befitting burial",
      "take good care of her children",
      "take another wife",
      "allow Nnu Ego marry a man of her choice",
    ],
    answer: "allow Nnu Ego marry a man of her choice",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s *The Joy of Motherhood*.",
    question:
      "The little money Nnaife makes after returning from Fernando PO is used for",
    options: [
      "expanding Nnu Ego's business",
      "taking care of his family",
      "sending his children to school",
      "getting more wives",
    ],
    answer: "taking care of his family",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question: "The movement in Adeoti's *Naked Soles* is characterized by",
    options: [
      "hope and agreement",
      "freedom and self-determination",
      "pricks and tears",
      "disappointed and disarray",
    ],
    answer: "freedom and self-determination",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question:
      "One of the dominant themes in Rubadiri's *An African Thunderstorm* is the",
    options: [
      "relationship between man and woman",
      "activities of man during rainy seasons",
      "effect of rain on women and children",
      "problem of climate change",
    ],
    answer: "effect of rain on women and children",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question:
      "In Kunene's *A Heritage of Liberation*, the weapons are to be preserved for the generation yet unborn by the",
    options: ["gods", "elders", "people", "government"],
    answer: "elders",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question: "Give Me The Minstrel's Seat ends on a clarion call for",
    options: ["freedom", "peace", "rectitude", "commitment"],
    answer: "freedom",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question:
      '"...the youthful hue/sits on thy skin like a morning dew..." The excerpt above from Marvell\'s *To His Coy Mistress* is an example of',
    options: ["simile", "anaphora", "paradox", "onomatopoeia"],
    answer: "simile",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question: "In Lawrence's *Bat*, the poet compares bats with",
    options: ["sparrows", "swans", "swallows", "crows"],
    answer: "swallows",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question:
      "Eliot's *The Journey of the Magi* could be said to examine the issues of",
    options: [
      "three trees on the low sky",
      "empty wine-skins",
      "spiritual rebirth",
      "holy pilgrimage",
    ],
    answer: "spiritual rebirth",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question:
      '"We would be believing we dreamt it" The figure of speech in the line above from Acquah\'s *In the Navel of the Soul* is',
    options: ["apostrophe", "assonance", "antithesis", "alliteration"],
    answer: "antithesis",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question: "The casualties in Lanko's *End of the War*",
    options: ["women", "children", "men", "soldiers"],
    answer: "children",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from Johnson, R, et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyinka, W. (ED.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; U. Maduka, C.T et al: Exam Focus: Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D.I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G: Naked Soles.",
    question: "The theme of Cope's *Sonnet VII* is",
    options: [
      "art of poetry",
      "adventure",
      "contempt for literature",
      "isolation",
    ],
    answer: "isolation",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "A literary work in which the characters and events are used as symbols is known as",
    options: ["characterization", "allegory", "metaphor", "parallelism"],
    answer: "allegory",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "Characterization in a novel refers to the",
    options: [
      "writer's opinion of the characters",
      "way the characters are revealed to the reader",
      "characters and the way they behave",
      "reader's opinion of the characters",
    ],
    answer: "way the characters are revealed to the reader",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "In literary work, verbal irony refers to a",
    options: [
      "device in which the speaker means the opposite of what he says",
      "situation in which a character speaks or acts against the trend of events",
      "difficult situation which defies a logical or rational resolution",
      "device in which the actor on stage means exactly what he says",
    ],
    answer: "device in which the speaker means the opposite of what he says",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "In the theater, words spoken by a character that are meant to be heard by the audience but not by the other characters on stage is called",
    options: ["aside", "soliloquy", "acoustic", "tone"],
    answer: "aside",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "Drama is the representation of a complete series of actions by means of",
    options: [
      "movement and gesture for the screen and audience",
      "speech, movement and gesture for the stage only",
      "speech, movement and gesture for the stage, screen and radio",
      "speech, gesture and movement for the screen and radio",
    ],
    answer: "speech, movement and gesture for the stage, screen and radio",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "A poet's use of regular rhythm is known as",
    options: ["allegory", "assonance", "metre", "onomatopoeia"],
    answer: "metre",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "A literary genre which directly imitates human action is",
    options: ["drama", "comedy", "prose", "poetry"],
    answer: "drama",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "A fable is a story in which",
    options: [
      "allegations are made about characters",
      "animals or things are used as characters",
      "there is an important setting",
      "the story is told in poetic form",
    ],
    answer: "animals or things are used as characters",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The juxtaposition of two contrasting ideas in a line of poetry is",
    options: ["euphemism", "synecdoche", "catharsis", "oxymoron"],
    answer: "oxymoron",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on general Literary Principles.",
    question: "The main aim of caricature is to",
    options: ["describe", "expose", "emphasize", "ridicule"],
    answer: "ridicule",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "O! Ceremony, show me but thy worth What is thy soul of adoration. The figure of speech in the lines above is",
    options: ["antithesis", "invocation", "personification", "apostrophe"],
    answer: "apostrophe",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "What eyes will watch our large mouths, Shaped by the laughter of big children What eyes will watch our large mouths? Birage Diop: Vanity. The tone of the lines above is one of",
    options: ["sarcasm", "sacrilege", "chiasmus", "eulogy"],
    answer: "sarcasm",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "The old man slept in his favourite chair The wind ran its fingers through his hair He looked like a tree gone dry of sap And his hands were dry upon his lap. The rhyme scheme of the poem above is",
    options: ["bbaa", "aabb", "abab", "baba"],
    answer: "aabb",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "Unequal laws unto a savage race, That board, and sleep, and feed.... The lines above show that the speaker",
    options: [
      "detects discrimination",
      "is desirous of adventure",
      "hates his old wife",
      "knows much of his city men",
    ],
    answer: "detects discrimination",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "How can I look at Oyo and say I hate long shiny cars? How can I come to the children and despise international schools? And Koomson comes, and the family sees Jesus Christ in him.... The feeling conveyed by the speaker above is one of",
    options: ["anger", "alienation", "hope", "despair"],
    answer: "alienation",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "Hide me now, when night children haunt the earth. Wole Soyinka: Night. Night children in the stanza above reflects the consciousness of",
    options: ["birds", "armed robbers", "animals", "spirit beings"],
    answer: "spirit beings",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "Serrated shadows, through dark leaves, Til, bathed in warm suffusion of your dapped cells Sensation pained me, faceless, silent as night thieves. Wole Soyinka: Night. The dominant mood in the lines above is one of",
    options: ["apprehension", "defiance", "joy", "indifference"],
    answer: "apprehension",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "The drums overwhelmed the guns... J.P Clark: Casualties. The poet in the excerpt above uses",
    options: ["litotes", "symbolism", "onomatopoeia", "alliteration"],
    answer: "symbolism",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "They do not see the funeral piles At home eating up the forests... J.P. Clark: Casualties. The imagery created in the above excerpt is achieved through",
    options: ["metaphor", "personification", "synecdoche", "metonym"],
    answer: "personification",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on selected poems.",
    question:
      "I cannot rest from travel: I will drink Life to the lees, all times I have enjoyed Greatly, have suffered greatly. A.L. Tennyson: Ulysses. The lines above inform the reader that the poet",
    options: [
      "is determined to suffer",
      "has his poetic imagination kindled",
      "will cure his sour mood",
      "will not drink much",
    ],
    answer: "has his poetic imagination kindled",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question: "Nnu Ego is blamed for the misfortunes of her",
    options: ["parents", "husband", "siblings", "children"],
    answer: "children",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question: "According to the novel, Nnaife becomes frustrated when",
    options: [
      "Oshiaju secures a scholarship to study abroad",
      "he is arrested and charged for attempted murder of his in-law",
      "his wife gives birth to female twins",
      "he is recruited into the army",
    ],
    answer: "his wife gives birth to female twins",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s The Joy of Motherhood.",
    question: "Adaku remains faithful to Nnaife until she",
    options: [
      "starts keeping unnecessary friends",
      "is unable to give birth to a male child",
      "is rebuked by the Ibuza society for abusing Nnu Ego",
      "becomes rich and powerful",
    ],
    answer: "is unable to give birth to a male child",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell’s Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The Ministry of Love is concerned with",
    options: [
      "peace and freedom",
      "torture and pain",
      "joy and peace",
      "hatred and pain",
    ],
    answer: "torture and pain",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell’s Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The instruments of power and torture belong to",
    options: [
      "the government",
      "the party",
      "the thought police",
      "individuals",
    ],
    answer: "the party",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell’s Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "The action in the novel is built around",
    options: ["Winston Smith", "O'Brien", "Julia", "Big Brother"],
    answer: "Winston Smith",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on George Orwell’s Nineteen Eighty-four.",
    question: "Winston Smith works in the Record Department of the Ministry of",
    options: ["love", "truth", "peace", "plenty"],
    answer: "truth",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "The dominant poetic technique employed in Adeoti's Naked Soles is",
    options: ["zeugma", "oxymoron", "hyperbole", "onomatopoeia"],
    answer: "zeugma",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question: "Rubadiri's An African Thunderstorm can be described as",
    options: ["didactic", "dramatic", "traditional", "satirical"],
    answer: "dramatic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "'Since it was you who in all these thin seasons.' The device employed in the line above from Kunene's The Heritage of Liberation, is an example of",
    options: ["apostrophe", "allusion", "anecdote", "aside"],
    answer: "allusion",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "'Let me ask for what reason or rhyme women refuse to marry? Woman cannot exist except by man, what is there in that to vex some of them so?' The lines above from Give Me The Minstrel's Seat is an example of",
    options: [
      "pathetic fallacy",
      "chiasmus",
      "ironical statement",
      "rhetorical question",
    ],
    answer: "rhetorical question",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "'Time winged chariot.' The line above from Marvell's To His Coy Mistress depicts",
    options: [
      "how fast time flies",
      "the usefulness of time",
      "the measurement of time",
      "how fast events unfold",
    ],
    answer: "how fast time flies",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question: "Lawrence's Bat opens with the description of the",
    options: ["scene", "creatures", "bats", "scenery"],
    answer: "bats",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question: "The theme of Eliot's The Journey of Magi is",
    options: [
      "quest for salvation",
      "escape from persecution",
      "nature",
      "journey",
    ],
    answer: "quest for salvation",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question: "Acquah's In The Navel of the Soul describes the",
    options: [
      "lack of experienced midwives in the society",
      "excesses of the new generation churches and politicians",
      "complications of motherhood and child bearing",
      "conflict between the church and tradition",
    ],
    answer: "complications of motherhood and child bearing",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "'Listen...they will tell you...to beat drums is mere children's play, the adult's is to start echoes...' The lines above from Launkos' End of the War, enhance the -----",
    options: [
      "rhyme of the poem",
      "rhythm of the poem",
      "language of the poem",
      "use of imagery",
    ],
    answer: "rhythm of the poem",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on selected poems from various anthologies.",
    question:
      "The language OF Cope’s Sonnet VII past event in a literary work is",
    options: ["complicated", "simple", "poetic complicated", "difficult"],
    answer: "complicated",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question:
      "A device used by a writer to recall past events in a literary work is",
    options: ["interlude", "anti-climax", "flashback", "foreshadowing"],
    answer: "flashback",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question: "A paragraph in prose is equivalent to a",
    options: [
      "trope in poetry",
      "verse in poetry",
      "stanza in poetry",
      "meter in poetry",
    ],
    answer: "stanza in poetry",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question: "A fable is a brief narrative illustrating wisdom and",
    options: ["urgency", "origin", "custom", "truth"],
    answer: "truth",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question:
      "A device used in poetry to achieve emphasis or stress a point is known as",
    options: ["rhyme", "assonance", "repetition", "alliteration"],
    answer: "repetition",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question:
      "A literary work that ridicules the shortcomings of people or ideas is",
    options: ["a masque", "a satire", "an irony", "a fable"],
    answer: "a satire",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question:
      "The figure of speech in which the writer means the exact opposite of what he intends to say is",
    options: ["satire", "irony", "paradox", "metaphor"],
    answer: "irony",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question: "Action without speech in a play is",
    options: ["soliloquy", "aside", "epilogue", "mime"],
    answer: "mime",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question: "A literary work that teaches a moral is said to be",
    options: ["impressive", "didactic", "instructive", "corrective"],
    answer: "didactic",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question:
      "A mistake committed by the hero which leads to his downfall is known as",
    options: ["comic relief", "terse", "climax", "tragic flaw"],
    answer: "tragic flaw",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literacy Principles.",
    question: "The speech made by a character to himself on stage is",
    options: ["monologue", "epilogue", "aside", "soliloquy"],
    answer: "soliloquy",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the question.",
    question: "The lines above show that the persona",
    options: [
      "does not understand the girl's language",
      "is so much in love with the girl",
      "so hates the words of the girl",
      "understands the girl's songs",
    ],
    answer: "does not understand the girl's language",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the question.",
    question: "The line ends in a literary device known as",
    options: ["transferred epithet", "rhetorical question", "irony", "conceit"],
    answer: "rhetorical question",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the question.",
    question: "The literary device used in the first line is",
    options: ["passion", "apostrophe", "burlesque", "rhetoric"],
    answer: "apostrophe",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Use the quotation below to answer the question.",
    question: "From the lines above, the poet sees the sun as",
    options: [
      "a necessary evil",
      "a light provider",
      "illumination after darkness",
      "an unnecessary evil",
    ],
    answer: "an unnecessary evil",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Femi Osofisan's Women of Owu.",
    question: "In the play, the gods are portrayed as",
    options: [
      "helpless",
      "architects of man's destiny",
      "amorous",
      "saviours of mankind",
    ],
    answer: "architects of man's destiny",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Femi Osofisan's Women of Owu.",
    question: "Orisaye describes Balogun Kusa as",
    options: [
      "a great warrior",
      "an enemy and a butcher",
      "a friend in need",
      "a good leader",
    ],
    answer: "an enemy and a butcher",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Femi Osofisan's Women of Owu.",
    question: "Erelu is",
    options: [
      "the oldest wife of the Oba Akinjobi",
      "a courtier to the Alaafin of Oyo",
      "the most brilliant woman in Owu",
      "the first wife of the Oba",
    ],
    answer: "the oldest wife of the Oba Akinjobi",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Femi Osofisan's Women of Owu.",
    question: "Balogun Kusa is killed by a",
    options: ["god", "herbalist", "lunatic", "soldier"],
    answer: "soldier",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's The Tempest.",
    question: "In the play, Ariel is identified as",
    options: [
      "leader of the spirits",
      "Prospero's daughter",
      "Alonso's wife",
      "assistant to Sycorax",
    ],
    answer: "leader of the spirits",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's The Tempest.",
    question:
      "Before the shipwreck that occurs at the beginning of the play, Prospero and his daughter have lived on the Island for",
    options: ["two decades", "twelve years", "forty days", "eighteen months"],
    answer: "twelve years",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's The Tempest.",
    question:
      "Caliban's intention to rape Miranda is born out of the desire to",
    options: [
      "destroy the Island",
      "compete with Ferdinand",
      "populate the Island with Calibans",
      "marry her",
    ],
    answer: "populate the Island with Calibans",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's The Tempest.",
    question: "The character associated with savagery in the play is",
    options: ["Ariel", "Stephano", "Caliban", "Ferdinand"],
    answer: "Caliban",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on William Shakespeare's The Tempest.",
    question: "Prospero is portrayed as a man who is",
    options: [
      "full of mistrust for everybody",
      "more interested in studying than in governance",
      "dependent on the spirits for his survival",
      "eager to conquer the world",
    ],
    answer: "more interested in studying than in governance",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Asare Konadu's A Woman in Her Prime.",
    question: "The novel explores the theme of",
    options: [
      "exploitation of the African woman",
      "sex discrimination in Ghana",
      "women liberation in Nigeria",
      "child quest of an African woman",
    ],
    answer: "child quest of an African woman",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Asare Konadu's A Woman in Her Prime.",
    question:
      "According to the novel, the worst calamity that can befall a woman is",
    options: [
      "inability to bear male children",
      "inability to marry",
      "divorce",
      "barrenness",
    ],
    answer: "barrenness",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Asare Konadu's A Woman in Her Prime.",
    question: "In the novel, Asogo is a game in which",
    options: [
      "fathers narrate animal stories",
      "boys abuse girls with music",
      "girls sing songs of praise and admonition",
      "mothers lure their babies to sleep",
    ],
    answer: "girls sing songs of praise and admonition",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Chimamanda Adichie's *Purple Hibiscus*.",
    question:
      "In the novel, one of the changes introduced into St. Agnes’ church by Father is that",
    options: [
      "there must be fasting every month",
      "the Credo must be recited in Igbo",
      "the Kyrie must be rendered only in Latin",
      "everyone must take holy communion",
    ],
    answer: "the Kyrie must be rendered only in Latin",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Chimamanda Adichie's *Purple Hibiscus*.",
    question: "Eugene Achike in the novel is portrayed as",
    options: [
      "a soft and gentle husband",
      "an uncompromising traditionalist",
      "a fanatical Catholic adherent",
      "a tough retired soldier",
    ],
    answer: "a fanatical Catholic adherent",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Chimamanda Adichie's *Purple Hibiscus*.",
    question:
      "In the Achike family, the character who is central to the theme is",
    options: ["Kambili", "Mama", "Sisi", "Jaja"],
    answer: "Kambili",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "The dominant image in Adeoti's *Hard Lines* is",
    options: ["auditory", "gustatory", "visual", "tactile"],
    answer: "visual",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "The tone of Umeh's *Ambassadors of Poverty* can be described as",
    options: ["metaphorical", "sarcastic", "admonitory", "panegyrical"],
    answer: "sarcastic",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "In Owonibi's *Homeless, not Hopeless*, the persona explains that street beggars",
    options: [
      "always worry about heaven",
      "rarely sleep and dream",
      "attend conferences in towns",
      "are concerned with their daily needs",
    ],
    answer: "are concerned with their daily needs",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "Cheney-Coker's *Myopia* is a",
    options: ["dirge", "lament", "sonnet", "ballad"],
    answer: "lament",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "Jared Angira is an African poet from",
    options: ["Sierra-Leone", "Kenya", "South Africa", "Ghana"],
    answer: "Kenya",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "The dominant technique used in *Serenade* is",
    options: ["metaphor", "simile", "oxymoron", "apostrophe"],
    answer: "apostrophe",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question:
      "The sun in Donne's *The Sun Rising* is depicted through the use of",
    options: ["invocation", "ellipsis", "enjambment", "apostrophe"],
    answer: "apostrophe",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "In Raleigh's *The Soul's Errand*, the soul is portrayed as a",
    options: [
      "friend of suffering masses",
      "fearless message-bearer",
      "restorer of lost glory",
      "messenger of hope and peace",
    ],
    answer: "fearless message-bearer",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "The allusion in Hughes's *The Negro Speaks of Rivers* is mainly",
    options: ["biblical", "historical", "classical", "literary"],
    answer: "historical",
  },
  {
    instruction:
      "Question is based on Selected Poems from *Ker, D. et al (eds.) New Poetry from Africa*; *Soyinka, (ed.): Poems of Black Africa*; *Senanu K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry*; *Umukoro, M et al (eds.): Exam Focus: Literature in English*; *Ernubetine, A.E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides* and *Nwoga, D.I. (ed): West African Verse*.",
    question: "Fletcher's *Upon An Honest Man's Fortune* encourages people to",
    options: [
      "condemn soothsaying",
      "move in the direction of God",
      "accept soothsaying",
      "accept life as it is",
    ],
    answer: "accept life as it is",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "An action in a play that stimulates the audience to pity a character is",
    options: ["pathos", "parody", "pyrrhic", "props"],
    answer: "pathos",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Purgation of emotion, pity and fear is",
    options: ["epilogue", "exposition", "catharsis", "catastrophe"],
    answer: "catharsis",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "A device in drama where a character speaks alone is",
    options: ["apostrophe", "dialogue", "soliloquy", "aside"],
    answer: "soliloquy",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "A plot in a literary work is about",
    options: [
      "resolution of conflicts",
      "law of poetic justice",
      "character delineation",
      "causal arrangement of events",
    ],
    answer: "causal arrangement of events",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Tone and mood of a poem refer to",
    options: ["setting", "space", "locale", "atmosphere"],
    answer: "atmosphere",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "A funny incident within a serious situation is",
    options: ["tragicomedy", "tragic hero", "comedy", "comic relief"],
    answer: "comic relief",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "In literature, a flat character can be described as one who",
    options: [
      "dies abruptly",
      "achieves greatness",
      "is undeveloped",
      "undergoes changes",
    ],
    answer: "is undeveloped",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Dramatis personae in a play refers to",
    options: [
      "cast list",
      "protagonist and antagonist",
      "list of characters",
      "order of appearance",
    ],
    answer: "list of characters",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question:
      "The speech made at the end of a dramatic performance is generally called",
    options: ["a dirge", "a monologue", "a prologue", "an epilogue"],
    answer: "an epilogue",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on General Literary Principles.",
    question: "Which of the following is central to narrative fiction?",
    options: ["Objectivity", "Subjectivity", "Verisimilitude", "Dialogue"],
    answer: "Verisimilitude",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "He put himself in uniform, made one for his five-year-old son, and marched with the infant from dawn till noon every market day, on the main road singing 'Kayiwawa beturi…' The persona in the excerpt above is portrayed as",
    options: ["energetic", "a policeman", "a soldier", "abnormal"],
    answer: "abnormal",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "He is a faithful liar. The above is an example of",
    options: ["epigram", "oxymoron", "euphemism", "antithesis"],
    answer: "oxymoron",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "Fights by the book of arithmetic. The figure of speech in the line above is",
    options: ["hyperbole", "euphemism", "litotes", "innuendo"],
    answer: "innuendo",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "And when you trudge on one horny pad gullied like the soles of modern shoes, pads that even jiggers cannot conquer. Horny pads in the lines above is a reference to a",
    options: ["policeman", "madman", "sole of a pauper", "sole of a soldier"],
    answer: "sole of a pauper",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "'Lift not the painted veil which those who live call life: though unreal shapes be pictured there, and it but mimic all we would believe with colours idly spread behind, lurk fear.' P.B Shelley: Sonnet. The stanza above is an example of a",
    options: ["quatrain", "sonnet", "couplet", "sestet"],
    answer: "quatrain",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "'Busy old fool, unruly sun, why dost thou call on us through windows and curtains?' The most vivid figure of speech in the lines above from Donne's The Sun Rising is",
    options: ["simile", "diction", "personification", "pun"],
    answer: "personification",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The allusion in Hughes's The Negro Speaks of Rivers is mainly",
    options: ["biblical", "classical", "literary", "historical"],
    answer: "historical",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "In Adeoti's Hard Lines, sodium cyanide is",
    options: ["poisonous", "adhesive", "sweet", "fragrant"],
    answer: "poisonous",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "In Owonibi's Homeless, not Hopeless, the persona explains that street beggars",
    options: [
      "always worry about heaven",
      "attend conferences in towns",
      "are concerned with their daily needs",
      "rarely sleep and dream",
    ],
    answer: "are concerned with their daily needs",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The poet persona in Serenade is a",
    options: ["suitor", "mother", "spinster", "passer-by"],
    answer: "suitor",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "In Cheney-Coker's Myopia, peasants refer to",
    options: [
      "under-privileged masses",
      "politicians",
      "farmers",
      "rural dwellers",
    ],
    answer: "under-privileged masses",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "In Angira's Expelled, the poet persona laments the",
    options: [
      "loss of his property",
      "harrowing experiences from the stranger's visit",
      "presence of the strangers",
      "problems of his family and their economic implications",
    ],
    answer: "harrowing experiences from the stranger's visit",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "Fletcher's Upon An Honest Man's Fortune achieves its lyrical effect through the use of",
    options: ["synecdoche", "antithesis", "enjambment", "ballad"],
    answer: "enjambment",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "Rhythm is achieved in Raleigh's The Soul's Errand through the use of",
    options: ["metaphor", "alliteration", "repetition", "antithesis"],
    answer: "repetition",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The title of Umeh's Ambassador of Poverty is",
    options: ["repetition", "a simile", "an alliteration", "an irony"],
    answer: "an irony",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "The repetition of a consonant sound in quick succession for sound effect is",
    options: ["alliteration", "pun", "onomatopoeia", "assonance"],
    answer: "alliteration",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "A play in which the acts succeed one another without probable or necessary sequence is",
    options: ["episodic", "simple", "linear", "convoluted"],
    answer: "episodic",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "A technique by which a previous scene or action can be recalled in a play to shed light on the present action is",
    options: ["climax", "flashback", "interlude", "catharsis"],
    answer: "flashback",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "Criticism is a literary activity which seeks to",
    options: [
      "find faults in a literary work",
      "analyze and evaluate a literary work",
      "compare and contrast novels",
      "discover the beauty of a literary work",
    ],
    answer: "analyze and evaluate a literary work",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "A situation where an actor addresses the audience without the other actors hearing him is called",
    options: ["soliloquy", "chorus", "aside", "solo"],
    answer: "aside",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "A band of singers and dancers in drama who act as a link between the play and the audience is the",
    options: ["chorus", "clown", "playwright", "cast"],
    answer: "chorus",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "A character whose name is used as the title of the text is",
    options: ["antagonist", "round", "eponymous", "flat"],
    answer: "eponymous",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "In poetry, the term license implies",
    options: [
      "freedom to sell poems",
      "liberty the poets take with language",
      "approval given to poets to compose poems",
      "honor given to deserving poets",
    ],
    answer: "liberty the poets take with language",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question: "The person who takes the leading role in a play or novel is the",
    options: ["protagonist", "actor", "antagonist", "actress"],
    answer: "protagonist",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Literary Appreciation.",
    question:
      "A form of writing in which the poet writes with nostalgia about simple village life is",
    options: ["ballad", "romance", "epic", "pastoral"],
    answer: "pastoral",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'We all make decisions. Sometimes it is wrong, sometimes it is right.' The speaker in the lines above is",
    options: ["Afraid", "Excited", "Pessimistic", "Reassuring"],
    answer: "Reassuring",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Her neck is rope-like thin, long and skinny and her face sickly pale.' Okotp' Bitek: Song of Lawino. The style used in the lines is",
    options: ["Narrative", "Argumentative", "Dramatic", "Descriptive"],
    answer: "Descriptive",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Once upon a time son, they used to laugh with their eyes; but now they only laugh with their teeth, while their ice block-cold eyes search behind my shadow.' G. Okara: Once upon a time The lines above are expressive of",
    options: ["Friendliness", "Insincerity", "Jealousy", "Sympathy"],
    answer: "Insincerity",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'When she opens her heart the savior's image!' Traditional: Love Song. The allusion in the lines above shows",
    options: [
      "That the poet is a Christian",
      "That his love had a heart surgery",
      "The climax of love relationship",
      "The anti-climax of love relationship",
    ],
    answer: "That the poet is a Christian",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Ay, your times were fine times indeed you have been telling us of them for many a long year. Here we live in an old rumbling mansion, that looks for all the world like an inn, but we never see company.' Goldsmith: She Stoops to Conquer. The figure of speech in the world like an inn is",
    options: ["Irony", "Euphemism", "Simile", "Metaphor"],
    answer: "Simile",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'She gave out colanuts and together they ate to appease the angry earth and Amadioha spoke through lightning and thunder.' The figure of speech in the third line above is",
    options: ["Personification", "Simile", "Hyperbole", "Metaphor"],
    answer: "Personification",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Ay, your times were fine times indeed you have been telling us of them for many a long year. Here we live in an old rumbling mansion, that looks for all the world like an inn, but we never see company.' Goldsmith: She Stoops to Conquer. The figure of speech in the world like an inn is",
    options: ["Hopeful", "Frustrated", "Regretful", "Happy"],
    answer: "Regretful",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Her neck is rope-like thin, long and skinny and her face sickly pale.' Okot p’ Bitek: Song of Lawino. The style used in the lines is",
    options: ["Ridicule", "Admonition", "Anger", "Sympathy"],
    answer: "Ridicule",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Ah, sunflower, weary of time who contests the steps of the sun seeking after that sweet golden clime where the travellers' journey is done.' The figure of speech in the second line above is",
    options: ["Simile", "Metaphor", "Irony", "Hyperbole"],
    answer: "Metaphor",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'There is no art to find the minds construction on the face he was a gentleman on whom I built an absolute trust.' Shakespeare: Macbeth, The gentleman in the lines above",
    options: [
      "Annoys the speaker",
      "Fights with the speaker",
      "Detests the speaker",
      "Betrays the speaker",
    ],
    answer: "Betrays the speaker",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'A priest rushed forward and poured libation,... Having thus appealed to the keeper of the spirit world, they waited for results. Moments passed before the bearers could move again.' The incident is the",
    options: [
      "Sacrifice to make Pokuwaa pregnant",
      "Burial of Yaw Boakye",
      "Search for Yaw Boakye",
      "Search for the missing black hen",
    ],
    answer: "Sacrifice to make Pokuwaa pregnant",
  },
  {
    question: "According to the medicine man, Pokuwaa has miscarriage because",
    options: [
      "Kwadwo often beats her",
      "She is barren from birth",
      "Her mother does not offer thanksgiving sacrifice",
      "Kwadwo's mother is a powerful witch",
    ],
    answer: "Her mother does not offer thanksgiving sacrifice",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'A priest rushed forward and poured libation... Having thus appealed to the keeper of the spirit world, they waited for results. Moments passed before the bearers could move again.' The incident narrated above takes place",
    options: [
      "On the way to the stream",
      "At the market place",
      "Close to the cemetery",
      "At the village square",
    ],
    answer: "At the village square",
  },
  {
    question: "The central theme of the play is",
    options: [
      "Man and nature",
      "Heaven and earth",
      "Sin and forgiveness",
      "Slow and steady",
    ],
    answer: "Sin and forgiveness",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the play, Prospero leaves his Dukedom of Milan to devote his time to the pursuit of",
    options: ["Magic", "Knowledge", "Romance", "Recreation"],
    answer: "Magic",
  },
  {
    question: "Prospero's sense of justice is one sided because",
    options: [
      "While he is angry with Antonio, he enslaves Ariel and Caliban",
      "He wants his back, so he can rule again",
      "He sees his usurpation from one side",
      "He is unfair to Miranda",
    ],
    answer: "While he is angry with Antonio, he enslaves Ariel and Caliban",
  },
  {
    question: "An idea that recurs in the play is",
    options: [
      "People's love for power",
      "People's love for money",
      "Development of the Island",
      "Love at first sight",
    ],
    answer: "People's love for power",
  },
  {
    question: "Gonzalo in the play is",
    options: [
      "Antonio's brother",
      "A Milan Senator",
      "A Neapolitan Councillor",
      "Sebastian's co-conspirator",
    ],
    answer: "A Neapolitan Councillor",
  },
  {
    question: "In the play, the gods are portrayed as",
    options: ["Loving", "Just", "Jealous", "Indifferent"],
    answer: "Indifferent",
  },
  {
    question: "At the end of the play, Prospero chooses to",
    options: [
      "Go back to Milan",
      "Stay on the island",
      "Become a hermit",
      "Live among the natives",
    ],
    answer: "Go back to Milan",
  },
  {
    question: "The theme of alienation is evident in",
    options: [
      "Prospero's relationship with his daughter",
      "Ariel's relationship with Prospero",
      "Caliban's relationship with the Island",
      "The King of Naples' desire for power",
    ],
    answer: "Caliban's relationship with the Island",
  },
  {
    question: "The play's primary setting is",
    options: ["A ship", "An island", "A castle", "A village"],
    answer: "An island",
  },
  {
    question: "The author uses this play to illustrate the concept of",
    options: ["Revenge", "Redemption", "Isolation", "Freedom"],
    answer: "Redemption",
  },
  {
    question: "The emotional climax of the play occurs when Prospero",
    options: [
      "Forgives his brother",
      "Reclaims his Dukedom",
      "Releases Ariel",
      "Discovers his love for Miranda",
    ],
    answer: "Forgives his brother",
  },
  {
    question: "The play ends with Prospero's",
    options: [
      "Return to Milan",
      "Death",
      "Pardon of Caliban",
      "Abandonment of magic",
    ],
    answer: "Abandonment of magic",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which character represents wisdom and moral integrity in the play?",
    options: ["Caliban", "Ariel", "Gonzalo", "Sebastian"],
    answer: "Gonzalo",
  },
  {
    question: "The underlying conflict in the play revolves around",
    options: [
      "Power and control",
      "Love and hate",
      "Nature and nurture",
      "Freedom and servitude",
    ],
    answer: "Power and control",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Williams Shakespeare's Othello.",
    question:
      "'ill-starred wench, pale as thy smock, When we shall meet at compt.' The device used in the lines above is",
    options: ["simile", "pun", "metaphor", "paradox"],
    answer: "simile",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Williams Shakespeare's Othello.",
    question: "Othello kills Desdemona because the",
    options: [
      "former is jealous",
      "former's race is insulted",
      "latter is a witch",
    ],
    answer: "former is jealous",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Williams Shakespeare's Othello.",
    question:
      "Brabantio is opposed to the relationship between Othello and Desdemona because",
    options: [
      "he prefers lago",
      "Othello is a Moor",
      "Roderigo woos her first",
      "Desdemona is too young",
    ],
    answer: "Othello is a Moor",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Williams Shakespeare's Othello.",
    question:
      "'soft you; a word or two before you go. I have done the state some service, and they know't No more of that, I pray you, in your letters, When you shall these unlucky deeds relate'. The speech above is made when the speaker is",
    options: ["travelling", "sick", "dying", "eloping"],
    answer: "dying",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Williams Shakespeare's Othello.",
    question:
      "'0 heaven; How got she out? 0 treason of the blood. Father, from hence trust not your daughters' minds By what you see them act. Is there not charms By which the property of youth and maidhood may be abused?' The speaker of the excerpt above is",
    options: ["Brabantio", "Othello", "Gratiano", "Roderigo"],
    answer: "Brabantio",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Bayo Adebowale's Lonely Days.",
    question: "Windows in mourning in Kufi wear garments that are",
    options: ["red", "black", "white", "dull"],
    answer: "black",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Bayo Adebowale's Lonely Days.",
    question: "In the novel, the bage cap signifies everlasting",
    options: ["happiness", "sorrow", "freedom", "despair"],
    answer: "sorrow",
  },
  {
    instruction: "Question is based on Bayo Adebowale's Lonely Days.",
    question: "Yaremi's only son is",
    options: ["Alani", "Wande", "Olode", "Deyo"],
    answer: "Deyo",
  },
];
